## **Esteban Ordenes**



emordenes2014@gmail.com



954.470.1796



linkedin.com/in/estebanordenes



https://github.com/emordenes/DataAnalystPortfolio



https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/esteban.ordenes



https://eportfolio.greatlearning.in/esteban-ordenes

### **Summary**

Experienced Software Engineer with an extensive record working with the Microsoft technology stack. Certified in Data Science and Business Analytics and highly rated in SQL queries, as well as analytical and process-oriented skills. Has extensive knowledge in the development of SQL queries, data curation, wrangling, manipulation, and visualization. Ability to provide insights, analytics, and business intelligence used to advance opportunity identification, process reengineering.

Passion for problem-solving and leveraging data. Competent to work in any organization that aims to create impact and build meaningful relationships with its consumers. Looking forward to expanding career in Data Engineering, and brings 20+ years of experience as a Software Engineer. Major strengths are dedicated to providing sound and stable business data insights and solutions.

#### Skills

MS .Net/Core • C# • MVC REST API • Python 3 • Structured Data (RDBMS) • MS SQL • MySQL • PostgreSQL • CTE • Semi-Structured Data (JSON, XML) • SSIS • Pentaho Data Integration(spoon/kettle) • Angular Node.JS • Google Material Design • ASP.NET • Razor • Bootstrap • JQuery • MVC UI • Responsive design • Agile Methodologies • Root Cause Analysis • SDLC • CICD • Requirements Analysis • PySpark • Regression Modeling • Supervised Learning and Classification • Ensemble Techniques • Model Tuning • Unsupervised Learning • Python Visualization (matplotlib, seaborn) • Tableau • SSRS • AWS Redshift • Apache Airflow

### **Experience**



## Software/Data Engineer (Remote)

LexisNexis Risk Solutions

Aug 2017 - Nov 2021 (4 years 2 months +)

- Net Core MVC API. Develop C# REST Service endpoints for data inputs either from internal web clients as well as automated processes. JSON Serialization and Dependency Injection. TDD(Unit Testing)
- UI development Angular, Node JS, Google Material Design.
- Technical Lead on several projects within a team of 3 developers. Agile. TFS CICD.
- Responsible for support of data content acquisition, creating and maintaining spiders and crawlers for 50000+ recurring web resources. On-Call support and Root Cause Analysis.

- Python. Creating web crawlers, newsfeed scrapers, and file downloaders for content acquisitions. Also, used for exploratory data analysis and predictive modeling.
- MSSQL.(CTE) Extracting data and transformation, as well as providing queries and insights.
- Pentaho Data Integration (PDI) Suite. Create ETL pipelines and processes for acquiring data from internal sources, cleansing, and generating formatted data to various systems.
- Produce Exploratory Data Analysis and Modeling Techniques for technical teams to analyze system performance data to support Data Content Acquisition decisions to improve data collection. This led to improving data collection rates from 70% to 85%.
- Modeling techniques used, Logistic Regression, XGBoost(SearchGrid and Randomized),
  GradientBoost, AdaBoost, Hyperparameter Tuning, and Feature Importance.
- Gathering, sanitizing, organizing, and integrating data for production processing.
  Develop and support business solutions and provide insights for business users and stakeholders.
- Tableau Dashboard, and creation of daily reporting of system metrics, as well as KPI status reports.

## Software Engineer

NCCI - Apr 2016 - Aug 2017 (1 year 5 months)

- Design and develop ASP.NET applications in support of customer service and subscription-based services.
- MSSQL. Creating stored procedures for CRUD operations, and queries for web dashboards.

## Senior Software Engineer - Contractor (Remote)

Wealth Management Systems, Inc (WMSI) - A DST Company

Jun 2014 - Aug 2015 (1 year 3 months)

- Technical Lead Developer of Product Development Team on a specific retirement planning product. Team of 3 developers.
- UI development Razor, Bootstrap, JQuery, MVC, Responsive design, JSON Serialization.
- WMSI develops technology solutions that include IRA rollover services in the financial services industry including financial education, planning tools, and advisor solutions.
- Import data from multiple sources and ETL processing. This data would feed into WMSI's products, which later could be used for customer account credentialing
- MSSQL.Creating stored procedures for CRUD operations, and queries for web dashboards.

### Software Developer III

MTN, a Global Eagle Brand

Nov 2010 - Feb 2014 (3 years 4 months)

• Design, develop and implement a variety of software applications. These include web pages and services, as well as console applications and windows services. Agile.TFS.

- Participated in the support and development of a credit card capture and authorization platform that integrated telephony services into the credit card billing system.
- SSIS ETL processes for integrating and creating data pipelines from multiple sources, including telephony long-distance systems. This migration required an understanding of the Porta-One system and integrating activity logs into the Dynamics GP (Great Plains) billing module and Dynamics CRM platform.
- MSSQL. Creating stored procedures for CRUD operations, and queries for web dashboards, as well as daily operations requests. Assisted SSRS reporting team with queries and insights.
- MySQL. Integrating Porta-One data in various Credit Card billing systems.
- Dynamics CRM. Creation of plug-in modules (VB) into Dynamics workflow modules.
- SSRS.Worked with Business Units and BI Team to produce scheduled and ad-hoc reports



# Sr. Software Engineer

### US Installation Group

Aug 2008 - Oct 2010 (2 years 3 months)

- Contributor of the Software Development Team for a service provider for The Home Depot.
- Designed, Documented, developed, and implemented a variety of software applications. These include web pages and windows services, as well as console applications.
- Next Generation Project. UI changes, as well as redesigning and enhancing the back-end processes (from classic ASP to .NET) and implementing new business requirements. WCF.
- Directly involved in various applications such as the Installer Compliance module, Bale Recycling System, Voice-Of-Customer and Inventory reports, Account Payables, and the automation of the workflow for The Home Depot purchase orders.



# Sr. Software Engineer

### Kaplan

Jul 2006 - Aug 2008 (2 years 2 months)

- Worked with the Post-Enrollment Academics Development Team.
- Participated in the design and development of many projects that add-on to the Student Portal web site where its main function is for students to log in and attend classes as well as manage all information regarding the student and faculty. WCF XML Serialization.
- Direct supporting Student Aid and Ledger Card, Instructor Concerns, Faculty Information Management, Student Assessment Portfolio Management.
- Key participation in the development of the Faculty Information Management System (Phase I) that would manage instructors' academia and courses integrating external systems such as PeopleSoft and Kenexa Brassring. The newly implemented system significantly decreased the administration's effort of keeping track of faculty's academic information.

### **Education**



The University of Texas at Austin (2021)

Post Graduate Program, Data Science and Business Analytics



# Universidad Tecnológica Metropolitana

Bachelor Science, Information Technology (Chile, 1996 - 2000)



## DUOC UC

Associates Degree, IT Systems Analysis (Chile, 1992 - 1995)

### Languages

Spanish: Native

### **Continuing Education**

Datacamp.com

- Data Engineering
- PostgreSQL
- Apache Spark
- Apache Airflow

#### Azure Cloud

Azure Fundamentals

#### PowerBI

AWS

Redshift